兄さん やっぱりここにいたんだ
I thought I would find you here.
Joanna, my sister.
ああ ヨハンナ
Please sit.
お座り
Listen to this:
ちょっと聞いて
“You are a holy people to Jehovah your God,
「あなたの神エホバにとって
あなたは聖なる民……
“and Jehovah your God
has chosen you to become his people,
エホバは すべての民の中から
あなたを選んでご自分の民とし
“his special property,
out of all the peoples
who are on the face of the earth.”
特別な所有物とされた」
The words of Moses,
約束の地に入る前
モーセが民に言った言葉
speaking to our people
before they entered this land.
Yes.
And just before that,
そう
モーセはその前に カナン人の偶像を
すべて打ち壊すように命じた
he told them to destroy
all the idols of the Canaanites.
I wonder if there are more idols
in the land now than there were then.
今その頃よりたくさん偶像が
あるんじゃないかな？
どこを見ても 民は
偶像に身をかがめている
At every turn,
our people bow and pray to them.
You’re doing all you can.
兄さんは頑張ってるよ
なぜこんな汚れたことを……
How dare you promote this filth!
でもみんなは聴かない
But they don’t listen.
まことの神は……
The true God . . .
やめろ あっちに行け
Stop right there.
わたしは聴いてるよ
I listen.
Moses came down from the mountain.
モーセは山から下りて来ました
Stop talking.
うるさい 黙れ
And I think you’re great.
兄さんはすごいよ
エリヤみたい
You’re like Elijah.
I’m surprised Jehovah uses me at all.
どうしてわたしのような者を
用いられるんだろう
Well, I’m not.
そんなことないよ
いつも正しいことをしようとしてる
You always want to do the right thing.
It makes us proud.
兄さんを誇りに思ってる
Jonah!
ヨナ！
は はい わが主よ
Ye—
Yes, my Lord.
Get up,
立って
大いなる都市ニネベに行き
go to Nineveh the great city,
and proclaim judgment against her,
彼らの悪がわたしの前に
達したことをふれ告げよ
for their wickedness
has come to my attention.
ニネベ？
Nineveh?
Nineveh.
ニネベ
滅びればいいんだ
They deserve to die.
It’s not his responsibility.
ヨナが行かなくても……
He’s just going to get himself killed.
行っても殺されるだけだ
You need to talk to him.
だれかが引き止めないと
Someone needs to talk to him.
食事にしないか
We’ve prepared a meal for you.
I’m not hungry.
食べたくない
They haven’t spoken a word to me in hours.
２人はぜんぜん話しかけてこないし
Your brothers are young, Jonah.
弟たちはまだ若いから
The news you brought to us this morning
今朝おまえから聞いたことに
圧倒されているんだ
—it was heavy.
What did your brothers say?
何と言っていた？
Izliah is afraid they will kill me;
イズリアは
わたしが皮をはがされて
殺されると心配してる
skin me alive.
He doesn’t think they should even be warned.
Just let Jehovah slaughter them all.
ニネベ人はエホバに
滅ぼされればいいって
エベルも彼らが警告を
聞くとは思っていない
And Eber doesn’t believe they will listen.
What do you think?
おまえはどう思う
I think that if it’s Jehovah’s will
to destroy them,
もしエホバが滅ぼすおつもりなら
わたしを遣わしたりされないでしょう
he wouldn’t have commanded me to go.
But I do think Eber is right.
でも ニネベが聞くはずがない
Why would they listen?
イスラエルでさえ聞かないんですよ
Our own people don’t listen.
でも神の警告は続いている
And yet the warning still goes out.
でも エホバが預言者を異国の地へ
遣わしたことがありましたか
But when has Jehovah
ever asked a prophet to go to a foreign land
to preach judgment against it?
裁きをふれ告げるために
Jonah, I—
ヨナ
わたしには理由は分からない
I don’t have all the answers.
確かにエホバは
To be sent to declare judgment
in the heart of Assyria,
これまで 裁きをふれ告げるために
アッシリアの都に行くようなことを
it’s unlike anything Jehovah
has asked of his prophets to do before.
預言者に求めることはなかった
But if it’s Jehovah’s will
that you should go,
しかしおまえが行くことが
エホバのご意志であれば
then you should go.
おまえは行くべきだ
He must have good reason
for sending you there.
それには十分の理由があるはずだ
神を信頼するんだ
Trust him.
Jonah!
兄さん！
兄さん！見て！
Jonah, look!
I got figs!
いちじくだよ！お菓子作るね
I’m going to pack you some cakes too.
わたしも一緒に行きたいな
I wish I could go with you.
イズリアは わたしが皮を
はがされて殺されると心配してる
Izliah is afraid they will kill me;
skin me alive.
You’re leaving without saying good-bye?
何も言わずに行っちゃうの？
You need to go back inside, Joanna.
家にいなさい ヨハンナ
But we had things prepared for you!
兄さんのためにいろいろ準備したんだよ
ニネベで要るもの
You’ll need them in Nineveh.
You’re not going to Nineveh, are you?
ニネベに行かないつもり？
No, Tarshish.
ああ
タルシシュに行く
No, Jonah!
だめ 兄さん！だめだよ！
That’s the wrong way!
Go back!
戻って！お父さんと話そう！
We can talk to Father!
ヨハンナ！
Joanna!
I can’t go to Nineveh.
ニネベには行けない
I just can’t do it.
無理なんだ
But what will you do in Tarshish?
でも タルシシュで何するの？
いつまでいるの？
When will you be back?
I don’t know, maybe never.
分からない
ずっとかな
Never?
ずっと？
Then who’s going to Nineveh?
じゃあだれがニネベに行くの？
Who’s going to tell them what Jehovah said?
エホバの言葉をだれが伝えるの？
I’m sorry, Joanna.
ごめん
エホバがどうされるかは
分からないけど
I don’t know what Jehovah will do.
But I just can’t do it.
わたしには無理だ
It’s too much.
エホバはわたしを必要とはしていない
He doesn’t need me anyway.
わたしには必要
We need you.
それに 兄さんはエホバの預言者
And you’re Jehovah’s prophet.
You’re like Elijah.
エリヤとおんなじ
そうでしょ？
Remember?
もう今は違う
Not anymore.
ヨハンナ ごめんね
Go home, Joanna.
I’m sorry.
おまえが行くことがエホバの
ご意志であれば おまえは行くべきだ
If it’s Jehovah’s will
that you should go,
then you should go.
Trust him.
神を信頼するんだ
Look!
うわあ！船長！
By the gods.
まずいな
帆をたため！
Furl the sail!
ロープを縛れ！ハッチを閉めろ！
Fasten those lines, men!
Hatches!
しっかりつかまれ！
Brace yourselves!
Secure the cargo!
積み荷を押さえろ！
Turn into the wave!
波に向かえ！
Captain, we’re taking on too much water!
船長！
水が大量に入ってきます！
Throw the cargo overboard!
積み荷を捨てろ！
全部だ！急げ！
All of it! Now!
捨てるんだ！
Get it over!
無駄です！
It’s no use!
これは神々のたたりだ！
This storm is from the gods!
Baal!
バアルよ！
Eshmun!
エシュムン様！
Melqart!
メルカルト様！
助けてください！助けてください！
Help us!
Where is the passenger?
乗客はどこだ？
He’s down below!
下です！
下にいます
He’s down below.
Please! Save us! Help us!
どうか！お救いください！
助けてください！
Why are you sleeping?
なぜ寝てるんだ
Get up, call out to your god!
起きて あなたの神に呼びかけてくれ！
Perhaps the true God
will show his concern for us,
まことの神が
顧みてくださるかもしれない
and we will not perish.
Save us! Help us!
Please, help us, Melqart!
お救いください！助けてください！
Please, help us! Baal!
どうか メルカルト様！
どうか 助けてください！
Save us! Save us! Baal!
バアルよ！お助けください！
Deliver us! Baal!
お救いください！バアルよ！
Let’s cast lots to find out
who is to blame for this calamity!
くじを引いて だれのせいで
こんな目に遭っているのか確かめよう！
あいつだ！
It’s him!
Why has this calamity come upon us?
なぜこの災いに遭っているのか
It is from the true and living God.
これは まことの神からのものです
神がこの嵐をもたらしたのは
わたしのせいです
He has brought this storm because of me.
Where do you come from?
あなたはどこから来たのか
国はどこか
What is your country?
どの民の人なのか
From what people are you?
I am a Hebrew,
わたしはヘブライ人で
and I fear Jehovah the God of the heavens,
海と陸を造られた
天の神エホバを恐れる者です
the One who made the sea and the dry land.
わたしはその方の預言者です……
I am—
I was his prophet.
いや
預言者でした
What have you done?
何をした？
He told me to go to Nineveh
and deliver a message.
ニネベに行って
宣べ伝えるように言われました
でも 逃げて来ました
Instead, I ran away.
What must we do to you
どうすればこの海は静まるんだ？
to make the sea calm down for us?
何をすればいいんだ？
What must we do?
Lift me up and throw me into the sea,
わたしを持ち上げて海に投げ込めば
and the sea will calm down for you;
静まるでしょう
for I know that it is because of me
この大あらしが生じているのは
わたしのせいだと分かっているからです
that this violent storm has come upon you.
投げ込もう！
Let’s do it!
死んでしまう！
He’ll die!
エホバの預言者を殺したら
ただじゃ済まないぞ！
If we kill Jehovah’s prophet,
what will He do to us?
If Jehovah wants him in Nineveh,
ニネベに行くべき人を海に投げ込んだら
won’t He be angered
if we throw him overboard?
エホバはお怒りになるんじゃないか
Take to the oars, men.
オールを持て！
Row for your lives!
死ぬ気でこぐんだ！
陸地が見えるぞ！
There’s the land over there.
急げ！
Hurry!
こげ！
Row!
It’s no use.
無理です
ヨナが言ったとおりにしましょう
We have to do what Jonah said.
エホバよ この人のために
わたしたちを滅ぼさないでください
Jehovah, may we not perish
because of this man.
罪のない血をわたしたちに
帰させないでください
Do not hold us responsible
for innocent blood,
あなたはご自分の喜びとなるように
事を行なわれたのですから
since you have done as you pleased,
O Jehovah.
あの人は代わりに死んでくれたんだ
He gave his life for us.
我々の神は 何もしてくれなかった
Our gods did nothing.
We should sacrifice
to his God for sparing us.
エホバに犠牲をささげよう
救ってくれたのだから
どうしてまだ生きてるんだ？
How am I still alive?
What will become of me?
わたしはどうなるんだろう？
エホバよ
O Jehovah,
out of the depths of the Grave,
シェオルの腹の中から
助けを叫び求めます
I cry to you for help.
Please hear my voice.
わたしの声を聞いてください
I know I have been driven
away from your sight!
わたしはあなたの目の前から
打ち払われました！
あなたの聖なる神殿を
どうして再び見ることがあるでしょうか
How will I gaze again upon your holy temple?
ああ わたしの祈りが
あなたのもとに届きますように
Oh, may my prayer come in to you.
わたしは 感謝の声をもって
あなたに犠牲をささげます
With a voice of thanksgiving
I will sacrifice to you.
自分の誓約したことを
わたしは果たします
What I have vowed, I will pay.
Hey!
おい！
Hey, are you OK?
おい 大丈夫か？
What happened?
どうしたんだ？
Are there others?
1人だけか？
しっかりしろ！
We’re here to help.
What is your name?
名前は？
Jonah.
ヨナ
ヨナと言います
My name is Jonah.
Grab his other arm;
we need to get him to the house.
そっち持って
連れて帰るぞ
パパが預言者って言ってた
Papa says you are a prophet.
預言者だった
I was a prophet.
Papa says that you
were swallowed by a big fish.
大きな魚にのみこまれたの？
Yes.
そうだよ
どうしてのみこまれたの？
Why would a fish swallow you?
Well, I was in the water.
海の中にいたんだ
なんで海の中にいたの？
Why where you in the water?
I was on a ship;
船に乗って それで海に入った
then I was in the water.
どうして船に乗ったの？
Why were you on a ship?
エホバから 逃げようとしたんだ
Because I tried to run away from Jehovah.
魚の中って 怖かった？
When you were in the fish, were you scared?
ああ
Yes.
Did you pray a lot?
たくさん祈った？
Yes.
ああ
神から逃げたのに
なんで神に祈ったの？
Why did you pray to God
if you were running away from him?
Father!
お父さん！
It’s Jonah!
兄さんが！帰ってきた！
He’s back!
Jonah!
兄さん！
Joanna.
ヨハンナ
I thought I wouldn’t see you again.
もう会えないと思ってた
I thought you wouldn’t be back.
帰って来ないと思ってた
ごめんね ヨハンナ
許してほしい
I’m so sorry, Joanna.
Please forgive me.
お父さんは毎日
兄さんの帰りを待ってた
Father waited for you to come home every day.
希望を捨てなかった
He never gave up hope.
What happened?
何があったの？
A fish?
魚？
あり得ないよ
How is that possible?
奇跡だったんだ イズリア
It was a miracle, Izliah.
Jehovah saved you.
エホバが救ってくださった
これからどうするつもり？
So, what will you do now?
I don’t know.
分からない
みんな少し休んだほうがいい
I think it’s time
for everyone to get some rest.
また明日話そう
We can talk more tomorrow.
兄さん
Jonah,
I’m sorry about the things
I said before you left.
出かける前にあんなこと言ってごめん
分かってなかったよ……
I didn’t realize . . .
気にしなくていい イズリア
It’s no matter, Izliah.
逃げたのは自分の決定だ
My decision to run was my own.
Thank you.
ありがとう
帰って来てくれて良かった
It’s good to have you back.
ああ ありがとう
Oh, thank you.
Thank you.
ありがとう
今も誇りに思ってる
I’m still proud of you.
しっかり休むんだ
Sleep well, my son.
Father?
父さん
Yes?
何だ？
頭から離れない
あの船乗りたち
I can’t stop thinking
about those men on that ship,
all the cargo they lost,
失われた積み荷
恐怖におびえた目
the fear in their eyes.
What if they didn’t survive?
もし助かってなかったら……
I put them in danger.
みんなわたしのせいだ
Disobedience often hurts others, Jonah,
不従順は 他の人も傷つけるんだ
not just ourselves.
自分だけの問題じゃない
We’ll pray for those men.
彼らのために祈ろう
Do you think Jehovah will ever use me again?
エホバはまた用いてくださるかな？
エホバは憐れみを示してくださった
He’s shown you mercy, Jonah.
He brought you home.
家に帰らせてくださった
Let’s be content with that for now.
今はそのことに満足しよう
父さん
Father,
I’m sorry.
ごめんなさい
大丈夫だ ヨナ
安心しなさい
I know, my son.
I know.
Let’s try to get some rest.
よく休むんだよ
Jonah!
ヨナ！
わが主よ！
My Lord!
I am so sorry.
お許しください
すみませんでした
Get up,
立って
go to Nineveh the great city,
大いなる都市ニネベに行き
and proclaim to her the message
わたしがあなたに語る
布告をふれ告げよ
that I tell you.
Yes.
はい
分かりました
Yes.
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
I will do as you command.
お命じのとおりにいたします
May Jehovah be with you, my son.
エホバが共におられるように
He saved me from the heart of the sea;
海の中から救ってくださったんだから
he can save me again in the days ahead.
この先も救ってくださる
Here, I made these cakes for you.
はい お菓子作ったよ
Thank you, Joanna.
ありがとう ヨハンナ
How long will it take you to get to Nineveh?
ニネベまでどれくらいかかるの？
If all goes well, maybe 40 days.
順調にいけば 40日かな
May it go well.
気をつけてね
ありがとう
Thanks.
Where are you traveling to?
どこまで行くんだ？
Nineveh.
ニネベです
本当に？
Really?
ちょうど行って来たんだ
I was just there.
Hmm.
へえ
馬を売りにね
I was selling some horses.
I’ll tell you this,
I’m glad to be going home.
正直言って 無事に
帰れるのがうれしいよ
You should really be careful over there.
向こうでは気をつけるんだね
そうですね
That’s what I’ve heard.
町はどんな感じですか？
Tell me about it.
Well, the city is huge.
まあ とにかくでかいよ
It would probably take you
three days to walk around it.
都市の周りを歩くだけで
3日はかかるだろう
兵車はまず世界最強だな
The chariots
—they’re the best in the world.
それから馬……
And the horses . . .
Hmm.
うん
The horses are magnificent.
馬も実に見事だった
人はどうですか
What about the people?
人ね
The people—
戦争の神を崇拝してるんだ
They worship gods of war.
大体分かるだろ
What do you think they’re like?
戦いと暴力が大好きで
They love conquest and violence;
それが生きがいみたいなもんだ
it’s like bread to them.
That’s comforting.
励まされるね
Hey, don’t worry.
心配するな
目立たないようにするんだ
Just don’t attract any attention to yourself.
仕事に集中してれば大丈夫だよ
Stick to your business,
and you’ll be just fine.
What is your business anyway?
で 仕事は何なんだ？
I’m a prophet of Jehovah.
エホバの預言者です
He’s sending me
to proclaim judgment against it.
裁きをふれ告げに行きます
Same thing again?
何してんだ？
It’s your fault!
あんたのせいよ！
Hello there, Foreigner.
こんにちは 外人さん
Where are you going, Foreigner?
どちらにご用？外人さん
待て！止まるんだ！
Hey! Stop! Stop!
My food!
泥棒！だれか捕まえて！
Somebody help me!
Thank you.
どうも
人はどうですか
What about the people?
戦争の神を崇拝してるんだ
They worship gods of war.
大体分かるだろ
What do you think they’re like?
In—
in just 40 days more,
あとわずか40日で
Nineveh will be overthrown.
ニネベは倒される
In just 40 days more,
あとわずか40日で
Nineveh will be overthrown!
ニネベは倒される！
だれ？あの外人
Who’s the foreigner?
In just 40 days more,
あとわずか40日で
Nineveh will be overthrown!
ニネベは倒される！
In just 40 days more,
Nineveh will be overthrown.
あとわずか40日でニネベは倒される！
Who can possibly overthrow our city?
この都市を倒せるもんか
気違いか？
Is he crazy?
イスラエル人みたいだな
He looks like an Israelite.
まことの神は言われた
The true God has spoken.
この都市の大いなる暴虐に
The great violence of this city
has come to the attention of the true God.
まことの神は注意を向けられた
Jehovah, the true God, has spoken.
まことの神 エホバは言われた
This city will be destroyed.
この都市は滅ぼされる
Nineveh will be overthrown.
ニネベは倒される
Jehovah, the true God, has spoken.
まことの神 エホバは言われた
Your city will be destroyed.
この都市は滅ぼされる
In 35 days,
あとわずか35日でニネベは滅ぼされる
this city will be destroyed.
Nineveh will be overthrown.
ニネベは倒される
この都市は滅ぼされる
This city will be destroyed.
あとわずか25日で
まことの神はニネベを倒される
We can’t just leave everything.
全部置いて行くなんて無理だ
どうすればいいんだ？
What should we do?
聞いてくれ！
Listen!
彼は イスラエルの神エホバの預言者だ
He is a prophet
of the Israelite God, Jehovah.
What should we do?
Should we flee the city?
都市から逃げるか？
We can’t just leave everything.
全部置いて行くなんて無理だ
家を捨てるの？どこに行けばいいの？
Leave our homes?
Where should we go?
まことの神はニネベを倒される
Listen.
悔い改めれば エホバは
憐れみをかけてくださるだろう
If we repent,
maybe his God will have mercy on us.
預言者によると 都市が滅ぼされるまで
あと20日しかありません
According to the prophet,
there are only 20 days left
until the destruction of the city.
民は エホバがどうすれば許して
くださるかを預言者に尋ねています
Throughout the city,
people are fasting and putting on sackcloth.
They are asking the prophet
how Jehovah wants them to behave,
人々は断食し 粗布をまとっています
and they’re trying to do as he says.
ヨナがそうするよう言ったのか？
Is that what Jonah is telling them to do?
いえ
No, the people simply reason
that because there’s a warning
警告も災いまでの猶予も
与えられたので
and time before calamity strikes,
神が考え直してくださると
思っているようです
maybe this God will change his mind.
What else have we learned about Jonah?
ヨナの情報はほかにあるか？
A Ninevite reported
overhearing a conversation of Jonah’s.
ヨナの話を聞いたとの報告があります
It seems he originally chose not to come.
この男は初め 来ないつもりで
タルシシュに逃げましたが
Instead, he fled to Tarshish
but was thrown overboard.
海に投げ出されました
Then he claims Jehovah sent a fish
to swallow him and bring him back.
エホバが自分を魚にのみこませて
救い出した と言っています
Is he insane?
ヨナは正気か
Maybe not.
ええ 恐らく
This man speaks for the God of Israel
この男はイスラエルの神
偉大さと力で知られた
奇跡の神の言葉を語っています
—a God of miracles,
known for his greatness and his power.
He might be powerful in Israel,
but we have our own gods here.
強力な神かもしれないが
我々にも神がいる
True, but Jehovah is the one responsible
そうですが エホバはエジプト軍を
紅海で滅ぼして
for humiliating the gods of Egypt,
その神々に恥をかかせた神です
even destroying their army in the Red Sea.
我々の歴史に残る大洪水も
エホバによるものです
He’s also the One
who brought about the great Flood
mentioned in our histories.
大洪水が引き起こされたのは
He did this because the people of the time
当時の人々が極めて
暴力的だったからです
were extremely violent.
書記官を呼べ
Call my scribe.
Help us, please!
Save us!
助けてください！お救いください！
I cannot accept gifts and bribes.
贈り物やわいろは受け取れません
Jehovah has spoken.
エホバは言われました
In 10 days more,
あと10日で
the true God will overthrow Nineveh!
まことの神はニネベを倒される！
The true God has spoken.
まことの神は言われた
The violence of the city
has come to the attention of the true God.
この都市の暴虐に
まことの神は注意を向けられた
The true God has spoken.
まことの神は言われた
ニネベは倒される
Nineveh will be overthrown.
The city will be destroyed.
この都市は滅ぼされる
ニネベの人々よ
王の言葉を聞きなさい！
Hear the word of the king, people of Nineveh.
Hear the word of the king!
言葉を聞くように
“By the decree of the king and his nobles:
「王とその大いなる者たちの
布告として伝える
“No man or beast,
人も家畜も 牛も羊も
“herd or flock, should eat anything at all.
いっさい何をも味わってはいけない
“They should not take food,
だれも食物を取ってはいけない
“nor should they drink any water.
水も飲んではいけない
そして 人も家畜も
粗布で身を覆うように
“Let them be covered with sackcloth,
“both man and beast;
力をこめて神に呼ばわり
“and let them call out earnestly to God
各自自分の悪の道から
その手の暴虐から引き返すように
“and turn from their evil ways
“and from the violence they practice.
まことの神が翻ってまさに悔やまれ
“Who knows whether the true God
“may reconsider what he intends to do
その燃える怒りから離れて
“and turn from his burning anger,
我々が滅びないようにしてくださる
ことはないと
so that we may not perish?”
だれが知っているだろうか」
あと3日で ニネベは倒される！
In three days,
Nineveh will be overthrown!
エホバは言われた！ニネベは倒される！
Jehovah has spoken!
Nineveh will be overthrown!
Something should be happening;
何かが起きるはずだ
there’s nothing.
でも何も起きない
Would Jehovah actually pardon the city?
エホバは本当にこの都市を
容赦されたのだろうか
No.
いや
No, that’s not possible.
それはあり得ない
どうしてエホバは考えを
変えてしまわれたんだ？
How could Jehovah change his mind?
人々はわたしのことをどう思うだろう
What will these people think of me?
What good is a prophet
if his words don’t come true?
語った言葉が実現しないなら
預言者に何の価値があるんだ
Was this not my concern
when I was in my own land?
ああ エホバよ
自分の国にいた時 わたしは
このことを心配していました
That is why I tried to flee
ですからタルシシュに
逃げようとしたんです
to Tarshish in the first place;
for I knew that you are
a compassionate and merciful God,
あなたが同情心と憐れみに富む神で
怒ることに遅く
忠節な愛に満ちておられ
slow to anger
and abundant in loyal love,
災いを悔やまれる神であることを
知っていたからです
and one who feels grieved over calamity.
O Jehovah, please take away my life,
エホバ
わたしの命を取り去ってください
for it is better for me to die than to live.
わたしは生きているより
死んだほうがましです
あなたが怒りに燃えたのは正しいことか
Is it right for you to be so angry?
I must leave the city.
この都市から出なければ
We know you are a prophet of the true God.
あなたはまことの神の預言者です
We have faith that you speak truth.
わたしの家に来てください
Please, stay in our home.
いや
No.
おもてなししますから
We will make you comfortable.
留まるつもりはない
I will not stay in this city.
Still nothing?
何も起きてない
This plant grew so quickly.
あっという間に育った
Jehovah still cares for me.
エホバの気遣いだ
O Jehovah, let me die.
ああ エホバ
わたしを死なせてください
命を取り去ってください
Take my life.
It is better
わたしは生きているより
死んだほうがましです
for me to die than to live.
Is it right for you to be so angry
over the bottle-gourd plant?
あなたがひょうたんのことで
怒りに燃えたのは正しいことか
I have a right to be angry,
わたしが怒りに燃えて死にたいと
思ったのは正しいことです
so angry that I want to die.
あなたは
自分が労したのでも
You felt sorry for the bottle-gourd plant,
大きくしたのでもない
ひょうたんを惜しんだ
which you did not work for,
nor did you make it grow;
それは一夜のうちに育ち
一夜のうちに枯れたものであった
it grew in one night
and perished in one night.
では わたしとしても
大いなる都市ニネベを
Should I not also feel sorry
for Nineveh the great city,
右も左も全くわきまえない
12万以上の人々に加えて
in which there are more than 120,000 men
多くの家畜もいる この所を
惜しんだとしても当然ではないか
who do not even know right from wrong,
as well as their many animals?
Are you Jonah?
あなたがヨナですか？
I am.
そうだよ
ママは あなたのおかげだって言ってた
Mommy says you saved us.
No, Jehovah saved you.
いや
エホバのおかげだよ
I was just—
わたしはただ
言われたことを伝えただけだ
I was just a messenger.
Thank you.
ありがとう
What are you doing?
何書いてるの？
I’ve written about Nineveh
ニネベについて
そして人々とわたしに対する
but also about Jehovah’s great mercy
both to the people there and to me.
エホバの大きな憐れみについて
Was it hard to write about all that?
書くの つらくなかった？
Painful.
つらかったよ
So, what will you do now?
これからどうするつもり？
Whatever Jehovah asks me to do.
エホバの言われることなら
何でもするつもりだ